<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Christopher Norman</title>
    <description>My development and programming blog.</description>
    <link>http://christophernorman.works/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://christophernorman.works/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 12:32:02 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 12:32:02 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cultivating a Healthy Writing Practice</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s code, novels, or a song - it’s always difficult to write with consistency. We all have our own baggage when it comes to writing. There’s so much that can gum up the works when it comes to getting out what you need to get out. It’s important to guard yourself against some possible pitfalls to keep things going. Here are a couple things that have helped me establish a healthy writing practice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consistency-is-key&quot;&gt;1. Consistency is key&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the boring one that we all expected, but it’s the truth. Humans are creatures of habit and like to be consistent. Steven Pressfield says in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stevenpressfield.com/the-war-of-art/&quot;&gt;The War Of Art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; that the only time your muse will come is when you show up consistently to work. This sounds kind of like a magical explanation, but I find it has everything to do with routine and state of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re doing something in a new space, distractions can pull your attention in a thousand different directions. This can make it difficult to do what you’re trying to do! It’s exactly like a bedtime routine. If you establish a consistent ceremony for it, you’ll slip into it without a second thought. Experiment! Figure out what &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; writing routine looks like. For some of us it’s the morning right when we wake up, for some of us it’s on the bus on the way to class (hello world!) - but whatever it is, try to make it consistent. Unless of course you thrive on chaos. Then never mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;write-now-edit-later&quot;&gt;2. Write now. Edit later&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you a perfectionist? Is it hard to even START writing sometimes? Then you might be trying to edit yourself while you write! Instead of focusing on what you want to say, you’re worrying about getting it right. STOP IT! I don’t know about you, but for me it’s much easier to edit than it is to come up with words out of thin air! So when you catch yourself, take a deep breath and start writing again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have trouble with this like I do, it’s important to nurture a gentle voice to remind you. The better you get at countering the “early-editor” the easier it’ll be to ease it into the process with confidence. Nothing kills the flow faster than judging yourself before you start. I’ve learned a good lesson about this while learning how to code. You’ve got to get it working first, then make it DRY (more efficient) once you’ve got the guts going. There are plenty of other metaphors. Would you paint your house before building your foundation? I’ll say it again: WRITE NOW. Fix it later. This leads nicely into…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;embrace-your-output&quot;&gt;3. Embrace your output&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An overlooked piece of cultivating a good writing practice is to make it enjoyable. One of the secrets to this is to roll with your output. I find I’ve wasted so much time writing what I &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to write instead of just writing. This is a manifestation of self-sabotage through resistance! No matter how much you want to create something like somebody else, you’re never going to. Unshackle yourself from those expectations and get on the path of least resistance. You’re trying to write a novel but haikus are all that’s coming out of you? Roll with it. Time for a haiku collection! Come back to that novel later. Only 3-chord ukulele songs happening for you right now? Wonderful! See where it goes. All you can write is a score for a horror clown opera? Roll with it! You get my point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember: you have a unique perspective - that’s going to be what makes your work interesting. We do ourselves no services by overriding our compulsions to create. Try to guide your output toward this path of least resistance. You may find yourself writing more and being happier at the end of the day. You can spend all day wanting to create something else, but at the end of the day what you have is what you made. Embrace it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-breaks&quot;&gt;4. Take breaks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been at it for a half hour and find yourself stuck, it might be a good time to take a break. Get some water. Stretch. Check your phone for a few minutes. If you’re able, go for a stroll. Go outside if you can! This &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; applies if you have volumes of writing to do at once. I’ve used the Pomodoro system before: 25 minute sessions followed by 5 or 10 minute breaks. This is particularly helpful for task-based writing work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no one size fits all strategy for this, so play around and see what works for you. For example, with creative writing it’s different. I’ll “get into flow” so to speak and won’t realize I’m working until hours later. Then I’ll take a walk and eat a snack before getting back to it. There are lots of variables, but regardless it’s important to take a break. Give your brain space to rest and your body time to move. When you start up again you’ll be primed and ready for action. You may even have solved a problem or two while letting your mind wander!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learn-when-to-let-go&quot;&gt;5. Learn when to let go&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’re writing a song (or story/code/etc), and by george if it isn’t the best damn one you’ve ever written. Look at you, killing it! So, of course, you invest a ton of time. You might even pull an all nighter to get that particular piece done. It’s not due for anything, you’re just feeling awesome about it. Cut to two weeks later. You’re still editing. You’re still tweaking. You know exactly what it has to look like, but it never seems to get where it needs to be. Sound familiar? It’s almost like gambling. “I’ve spent X amount of money and my time, it HAS to work out! Might as well double down again…” The hard news is sometimes it doesn’t work out. Not on your expectation of the timeline, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, I don’t want to tell you not to work through some blocks that a piece puts up for you. Sometimes you just need a little feedback. It’s a fine line between getting things right and never being able to let it see the light of day. If the end is near, then make it work! What I’m talking about here is when that end never seems to get any closer. When you’ve sunk in countless time and energy and aren’t getting anything out of it. This is when I know I’m too attached to an idea of what my piece can be to let it ever get done. If you find yourself in this situation, drop it and move to something else. You can always come back to something when you’re feeling more inspired. You even might want to start from scratch! Chalk up everything until now as a learning experience. You’d be surprised how quickly things come with a new start. You &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be willing to throw it out the window or come back to it if it isn’t working. Learn when to let go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-feedback&quot;&gt;6. Get feedback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein as #5, don’t get attached to your work to a degree that you have to shield it from critique. If you’re a hobbyist, there’s nothing wrong with staying in the tweak stage forever. Yet as scary as it is, this exchange of ideas is the single best way to improve your work. Sure, taking feedback can sometimes be painful. Especially for a piece you’ve poured your heart into. Remember: feedback is only another perspective for you to consider. It has no bearing on you as a person. The sooner you can welcome feedback with open arms, the sooner you can integrate it into your work. The result? You get tougher and your work gets better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;put-it-out-there&quot;&gt;7. Put it out there&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you write only for personal edification, there are few good reasons to not share your work. Your piece can’t grow if it spends its life in the dark! Whether it’s to a colleague for feedback or the public for consumption. In the same vein as #5, once things are out in the open it makes it difficult to keep tweaking. I find this makes it easier to keep moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not that you should judge yourself based on your productivity. It’s that you give your work a new life when you publish it. You’re creating things for a reason, aren’t you? Fear of sharing your work is another manifestation of resistance. Be vigilant! Share your work and then keep creating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These few tips have helped me write better and more consistently. What helps you get out of your way and start writing? Connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/misternorman&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and let me know what works for you!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 06:33:18 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://christophernorman.works/blog/2016/cultivating-a-healthy-writing-practice/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://christophernorman.works/blog/2016/cultivating-a-healthy-writing-practice/</guid>
        
        <category>blog, new</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
